hi and welcome to the book lab in this
video I'm going to talk about the stoic
system of Tom wolves a man in full and
also recommend a few other books that
will teach you more about this powerful
ancient philosophy
[Music]
sometimes here at the book lab we turn
to fiction and when we do we often turn
to books that can teach us something
about what it means to be human and the
human predicament and Tom wolves a man
in full is such a book and in this video
I'm going to talk about how the
discovery of stoicism in times of
adversity change the lives of the main
characters of this book a meaningful is
a novel by Tom Wolfe published in 1998
the book takes place in Atlanta Georgia
and explores themes such as the race
class masculinity power and the American
dream in the book we get to follow the
lives of a bunch of characters whose
lives are interconnected in various
different ways Conrad Hensley and
Charlie Krueger are two of the main
characters of a man in full and they
both have significant moments when they
come to realize the power of stoicism in
this book but who are these characters
first we have Charlie crooker our
wealthy 60 year old Real Estate Mogul
he's also a member of the Atlanta High
Society and he faces some financial
troubles and has a personal crisis and
then we have Conrad Hensley Conrad
Hensley is an idealistic young worker at
the Frozen Goods Warehouse that is run
by one of Charlie's subsidiary companies
Conrad is laid off suddenly due to
downsizing efforts that Charlie puts in
place in order to save his business from
bankruptcy so Conrad is laid off and he
has a really shitty day and
unfortunately he ends up in this Cafe
skin farcical parking hassle where he
butts head with the law and he actually
stands up for himself because he hasn't
done anything wrong really but because
he stands up for himself he refuses to
take a plea bargain he ends up in jail
so Conrad ends up in prison and in there
he requests the book from the prison
Library called the stoic game which is
supposed to be a spy novel of some sort
but the books gets mixed up and he
instead receives a copy of a book called
The stoics and that book contains texts
from
Epictetus and other famous story
philosophers at first Conrad is
disappointed by the mixer but when he
starts to read the book and he realized
that Epictetus has been through a lot of
like it's been uh Dave and he was
tortured and crippled by a slave owner
but still he went on and became one of
the most influential philosophers of
Imperial Rome when he read this his
disappointment turned to excitement and
he started to slowly learn Epictetus
stoic teachings
he learns that our bodies and
possessions are mere Trifles things that
are only on loan to us Seuss has given
us the spark of his own Divinity in the
form of our power of Rejoice we are
mortal and our bodies can easily be
conquered but our will cannot unless we
permit it difficulty and adversity are
moments of opportunity where we can
learn to persevere to practice or
resolve and our will we can endure any
hardship as long as we keep our dignity
our self-respect and what we see as our
character this book eventually
transforms Conrad into a full-blown
story what little Conrad knew about
philosophy felt like it was aimed at
people who already were free whose main
problem was to choose among infinite
possibilities in life
Epictetus on the other hand he made the
assumption that life is hard it's
punishing it's a deadly business
basically only a potatoes as far as
Conrad knew was a philosopher who had
been stripped of it all who hit rock
bottom who has been tortured and
crippled and yet he was the one to look
his tormentors in the face and say quote
you do what you have to do and I do what
I have to do which is to live and die
like a man
and the Victorious had prevailed this
mindset was very useful for condrent in
prison but most importantly of all
Epictetus understood he understood he
understood why Conrad didn't take the
plea bargain which had him ending up in
jail I mean his wife and his lawyer they
all wanted him to compromise and plead
falsely in order to avoid jail time only
a potatoes had understood why he refused
to lower himself to disgrace himself to
admit a minor crime in order to avoid
jail time
this book had a really big impact on him
and after reading it nothing in his life
was the same
for Charlie crooker his moment of
realization is
triggered by a different type of Crisis
he's a wealthy real estate developer
that is facing numerous legal and
financial issues
first he reacts to this with anger and
frustration even denial
but eventually he comes to see the
situation as an opportunity to reassess
his values his priorities in life and
how he lives his life he turns to the
writings of the stoic particularly
Marcus Aurelius and he begins to see
that his struggles is just a part of a
bigger
pattern of The Human Experience he
learns to accept his circumstances and
to find peace and meaning in the present
moment rather than constantly striving
for external success and validation both
conrades and Charlotte's realization
about the power of stoicism comes at the
pivotal moment in their character arcs
and they find that through stoicism they
find a new source of power and
resilience
overall a manifold uses historic
philosophy as lends to which to explore
the lives and experience of its
characters showing both challenges and
rewards of adopting a stoic outlook on
life we read a manifold or maybe you
watched the TV series I think it's
premiering soon on Netflix I think and
you become interested in stoicism and if
you want to know more then I have a few
book recommendations that are great
starting points for exploring stoic
philosophy
first out is a guide to the good life
this is one of my favorite books of all
time this is the book that introduced
stoicism to my life I've never read
about it before but this book is super
accessible for people who don't have any
prior knowledge of the philosophy it's
takes a teaching from this famous stoics
Rufus Marcus Aurelius Epictetus and
applies it to Everyday Modern Life so
it's a very practical book and it's a
very accessible entry point for anyone
who wants to learn about stoicism I'm
also giving away this book on my patreon
so if you want to support book club
besides liking and subscribing the video
on the video you can join patreon where
I give away books each month and this
month I give away this book it's
fantastic another great book that is
only 21 pages long that I really thought
about when I read a man in full is this
book James Bond stocked his courage
Under Fire testing epictetuses doctrines
in a laboratory of human behavior
uh James Bond Stockdale he was a fighter
pilot during the Vietnam war he got
captured he was a prisoner of war and he
was tortured during that time and he
used this teachings that he learned from
Epictetus Epictetus has a very famous
book called anciridion this was a book
that had a big impact on stock Tales
before he went there and when he was
imprisoned and tortured he Juiced
Epictetus teachings to endure to
persevere it's a super interesting short
story based on real life events and if
you want to read the original text then
I had two books for you
I would recommend sendikas on the
shortness of life because it's short and
it's
incredible how relevant this book is
even though it's 2 000 years old this is
an essay about the duration of Life Is
Life
short or is it long or is it just long
enough
sometimes we feel like life is short too
short to do anything remarkable Seneca
doesn't agree he says that life is long
enough if you know how to use this this
is a very accessible book as well the
funny thing about the stock is that
their books
are old and sometimes I associate old
with being hard or complicated to read
but that's not the case with Seneca so
check this book out it's a short and
sweet read I also recommend letters from
A stoic by Seneca it's another great one
I have reviews of all these books and
there's links to all those reviews in
the description I'll be back next week
with more book reviews I think one of
the upcoming books would be discipline
is Destiny by Ryan holiday his new book
are giving in another chance after this
thing his last title courage is calling
so let's see if he can redeem himself
anyway see you next week with more book
reviews until then pearn out
foreign
[Music]